[Music]
Professor Dave and CH here now that we
know what infrared spectroscopy is and
what simple IR Spectra depict it's time
to get more thorough and see how a wide
variety of functional groups will show
up on an IR spectrum first let's recall
what we are looking at the horizontal
axis tells us the wave number which is a
way of expressing frequency in inverse
centimeters so all the different
wavelengths of infrared light are
represented at different places on the
horizontal axis and the vertical axis
tells us the present transmittance at
that wave number if the transmittance is
very high almost all of that light got
through so almost none of it was
absorbed by the sample if the
transmittance is very low then very
little of it got through so most of it
was absorbed by the sample that is what
we see with these Peaks that dip down in
a pronounced way wherever we see these
Peaks we can be certain that the
corresponding functional group is
present in the molecule there are Peaks
that we will see over and over again so
let's simply list what they are give the
associated wave numbers and discuss
other characteristics when necessary for
alkanes an IR spectrum isn't too
interesting since all we have is the
saturated CH stretch and the CC stretch
most organic compounds have these bonds
so these Peaks will show up almost all
the time for alkenes we see stretches
for the vinyl proton and the
carboncarbon double bond there is also
outof plane bending for the vinyl proton
which helps determine the substitution
pattern with alkin we get a stretch for
the triple bond and the intensity tells
us whether this is terminal or internal
then for aromatic compounds we see
aromatic CH stretching there is also
data for the carbon carbon bonds in the
ring
itself moving on to functional groups
with hetero atoms there is the hydroxy
stretch this is perhaps the easiest to
spot of any functional group as the peak
will be very Broad and rounded which is
due to hydrogen bonding if you see this
and you can't miss it there is a hydroxy
group present amines have an NH stretch
that is easy to spot as well as it is
much sharper and less intense than the
hydroxy stretch car carbonal containing
compounds are also easy to spot as the
carbonal stretch is unmistakably long
and narrow the precise position of this
stretch will help us determine what kind
of carbonal it is whether aldah Ketone
carboxilic acid Esther amid or
otherwise once again every functional
group will have its own characteristic
Peak and we can refer to a table like
this to identify them we will never have
to memorize this information but the
characteris istic shapes of some of the
Peaks will be easy to remember all of
this allows us to figure out which
functional groups are on the molecule as
well as which functional groups are not
on the molecule if their peaks are not
present Professor Dave for see you next
time